A Guide to the Additional Papers of the Hammond Family 1805-1936
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Additional Papers of the Hammond Family 1805-1936
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
5395-b
This collection consists of ca. 1340 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers were a gift to the library from Mr. Lewis M. Hammond, the son of Kensey Johns Hammond, 1610 Meadowbrook Heights Road, Charlottesville, Virginia 22901 on 25 June 1976.
Scope and Content Information
The Additional Papers of the Hammond Family, 1805-1936, consist of 1.7 shelf feet (ca. 1340 items) of correspondence, papers, photographs, prints, newspaper clippings, and mementoes. Virtually all of the correspondence is between family members and is personal in nature. There are many letters from Anna Caroline Hammond to her children, Charles Howes Hammond and Mary Goldsborough Hammond, and from Mary to her nephew, Kensey Johns Hammond, an Episcopal minister. The correspondence of the latter concerns church as well as personal affairs and reflects his interest in genealogy. The papers include sermons, prayers, family tress, and notes on genealogy.
Organization
The papers arrived at the library in rough chronological order, and they have been arranged entirely chronologically. The correspondence is followed by the papers, drawing, photographs, and prints, newspaper clippings, postcards, souvenirs and mementoes, and one bound volume.
List and Identification of Family Members Who Appear in the Correspondence
Anna Caroline (Goldsborough) Hammond (1803-1861) wife of Dr. Nicholas Hammond, grandmother of Kensey Johns Hammond
Caroline Goldsborough Hammond (1861-?) daughter of Charles Howes Hammond and Julia Hammond, sister of Kensey Johns Hammond
Caroline (Machen) Hammond, wife of Kensey Johns Hammond
Charles Howes Hammond (1825-?) son of Dr. Nicholas Hammond and Anna Caroline Hammond, father of Kensey Johns Hammond
Charles Howes Hammond, Jr. (1868-1896) son of Charles Howes Hammond and Julia Hammond, brother of Kensey Johns Hammond
Julia (Johns) Hammond (1829-1892) wife of Charles Howes Hammond, mother of Kensey Johns Hammond
Kensey Johns Hammond (1858-1937) son of Charles Howes Hammond and Julia Hammond, Episcopal minister
Maria Johns Hammond (1862-?) daughter of Charles Howes Hammond and Julia Hammond, sister of Kensey Johns Hammond
Mary Goldsborough Hammond ("Aunt Mamie") (1829-?) daughter of Dr. Nicholas Hammond and Anna Caroline Hammond, aunt of Kensey Johns Hammond
Nicholas Hammond (1758-1830) father of Dr. Nicholas Hammond, great- grandfather to Kensey Johns Hammond, a prominent Maryland lawyer
Dr. Nicholas Hammmond (1795-1831) son of Nicholas Hammond and Rebecca (Hollyday) Hammond, husband of Anna Caroline Hammond, grandfather of Kensey Johns Hammond, a physician
Nicholas Hammond (1824- 1868) son of Dr. Nicholas Hammond and Anna Caroline Hammond
Contents List
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families including a letter from Charles Carroll of Carrollton to Nicholas Hammond 1805-1831, 24 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1836-1849, 27 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1850-1859, ca. 50 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1860-1879, 45 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1880-1889, ca. 40 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1890-1895, 46 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1896-1899, ca. 40 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1900-1911, ca. 80 items (Box 1)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1912-1918, ca. 30 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families 1919-1934, 36 items (Box 2)
- Correspondence of the Hammond and Johns Families ca. 1860-1936, 34 items (Box 2)
- Papers realting to the Hammond Family 1819-1929, ca. 50 items (Box 2)
- Papers of Kensey Johns Hammond: Registers and Programs from schools including Hampden- Sidney College and Johns Hopkins University 1873-1888, 11 items (Box 2)
- Papers: Sections of Julia Johns Hammond's Diary 1883-1884, 1 item (Box 2)
- Papers: The Parish Leaflet of various West Virginia churches, and Immanuel Church, Wilmington, Delaware 1885-1898, 1 item (Box 2)
- Papers: Sermons of Kensey Johns Hammond ca. 1886-1936, 9 items (Box 2)
- Papers: Sermons ca. 1886-1936, ca. 25 items (Box 3)
- Papers: Guest Book of Immanuel Church Rectory 1897-1911, 1 item (Box 3)
- Papers relating to the Genealogy of the Hammond Family 1840 (1900-1935), ca. 65 items (Box 3)
- Papers relating to the Genealogy of the Hammond Family ca. 1900-1935, ca. 70 items (Box 3)
- Photographs, including Charles H. Hammond, father of Kensey Johns Hammond, friends, and other individuals ca. 1865-1885, 18 items (Box 3)
- Pen and Ink Drawing of Trinity Church, Moundsville, West Virginia 1887, 1 item (Box 3)
- Photographs of the Laying of the Corner Stone of Trinity Church, Moundsville, West Virginia, and Trinity Church completed 1887, 1894, 2 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of the Theological Seminary of Virginia 1892, 2 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of Robert King Carter's Tomb, St. Mary's Church, Baltimore, Maryland, and unidentified churches 1893, n.d., 4 items (Box 3)
- [Photographs of Immanuel Church, Wilmington, Delaware?] 1905, n.d., 2 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of Kensey Johns Hammond 1921, 1935, n.d., 9 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of Pleasant Hill, Rixeyville, Virginia, home of Margaret Robinson Lewis, Communion and Baptismal Pewter of Lutheran Church, Madison County, Virginia, and other sacred vessels 1921, 1928, 1931, 3 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of Little Fork Church, Oak Shade, Culpeper County, Virginia 1928, 1931, 4 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of St. Stephen's Church, Culpeper, Virginia 1933, n.d., 5 items (Box 3)
- Photograph of St. Mary's Church, Franklintown, Maryland n.d., 1 item (Box 3)
- Photographs of Christ Church, Broad Creek, Sussex County, Delaware, and other unidentified churches n.d., 3 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of Hebron Lutheran Church, Madison County, Virginia n.d., 2 items (Box 3)
- Photographs of unidentified churches n.d., 7 items (Box 3)
- Print of the American Eagle ca. 1855, 1 item (Box 4)
- Print of The Baptism of Christ by Gerhard David n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
- Print of Canterbury Cathedral n.d., 1 item (Box 4)
- Prints of People, Historic Churches, and Homes n.d., 24 items (Box 4)
- Index pro Evangeliis Catholicis Matthew, Mark, Luke, also Index of Biblical Illustrations, etc. 1879, 1 item (Box 4)
- Newspaper Clippings ca. 1900-1935, ca. 300 items (Box 4)
- Postcards of Ireland, England, and Scotland ca. 1908-1910, 113 items (Box 4)
- Postcards of England, Germany, Italy, etc. ca. 1908-1910, 125 items (Box 4)
- Souvenirs and Mementoes ca. 1890-1930, 16 items (Box 4)
- Printed Matter
  - Hand Book of Christ Church, Philadelphia 1892
  - Christ Church in the Revolution 1892
  - Descriptive Catalogue of the Permanent Collections of Works of Art 1897
  - The Westminster Abbey Guide 1908
  - Picturesque Oxford 1908
  - A Short Guide to The Abbey and College of St. Augustine 1908
  - Guide to Oxford 1909
  - Publications of The Genealogical Society of Pennsylvania 1920
  - A Day in Durham n.d.
  - Canterbury Official Guide to the Catherdral Church and Handbook To The City n.d.
  - Signal Guide to Edinburgh n.d.
  - The Ancient and Royal City of Canterbury: The Official Guide n.d.
  - Notes on the Cathedral n.d.